We started a new פרק *perek* today. The דף *daf* is ע"ו
*ayin vav* 76. We start at the very bottom of ע"ה עמוד
ב' *ayin hey amud bet*. It says השוכר את האומנין *Hasocher et
ha'umnin*. You'll see the next פרק *perek* is called השוכר את הפועלים
*Hasocher et hapo'alim*. These are about labor law and responsibilities to workers.
אומנין *umnin* are craftsmen technically, and פועלים *po'alim* are more generically workers.
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* actually says that the word פועלים *po'alim* refers more
specifically to people that you pay a daily wage to, and אומנין
*umnin* tend to be more of an umbrella category, it can occur
both people that you pay a daily wage as your יום *yom*
and a קבלן *kablan*. A קבלן *kablan* is somebody that you pay
for the job. So just keep that in mind as in terms
of a possible difference of those words, but אומנין *umnin* of course
also more narrowly means like a craftsman. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
here says it more includes different types of workers. Okay, so let's
take a look. השוכר את האומנין *Hasocher et ha'umnin*, somebody hires workers
והטעו ve'hitu, זה את זה Zeh et zeh *vihit'u zeh et zeh*
and they tricked one another. So presumably that means the owner somehow
misled the workers or vice versa. We'll see what this means in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אין להם זה על זה אלא תרעומת ein
lahem zeh al zeh ela taroumes, *ein lahem zeh al zeh ela
tar'omes*. You only have a complaint against one another, but you do
not have any actual recourse in terms of a court of law
for financial compensation. Now of course the key question is what type
of deceiving are we talking
about, like the whole עיקר חסר מן הספר *ikar chaser min hasefer*,
tell me the specifics. Obviously there's some types of deceivings that should
be more consequential. And the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* now is going to
actually even go on to tell you about certain types of cases
in which there are going to be some actual financial
compensation. השוכר את החמור ואת הקדר *Socher et hachamor ve'et hakadar*, you
hired a donkey driver or a קדר *kadar* normally means somebody that
carries vessels, like a
porter. Well that's the thing, קדר *kadar* from the word normally does
mean specifically
like barrels or things like that, but here it just means a
wagon driver. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* either says it's because the people
that
carries pots and vessels often have wagons, or he says the גרסא
*girsa* might be קרר *karar* not קדר *kadar*. I don't know how
קרר *karar* means a wagon driver. But anyway, so you hired these
people, either a donkey driver or wagon driver, people that
are movers. Okay, so good Jewish movers.
להביא פריפרין וחלילין לכלה *lehavi priparin vechalilin lekalah* to bring פריפרין
*priparin*, which רש"י *Rashi* says
means some type of a nice type of
wood component for building a חופה *chuppah* or something of that nature,
וחלילין *vechalilin* and flutes לכלה *lekalah* either for a wedding או למת
*o lamet* or for a funeral. I assume that's more about the
חלילים *chalilim* because they would do that as a type of wailing
and so on at the funerals that they would play these flutes.
I don't know about this פריפרין *priparin*. Anyway, ופועלים להעלות פשתנו מן
המשרה *upo'alim lihalot pishtano min hamishrah* or you'd hire workers, here's the
word פועלים *po'alim* again, to get your flax out of the soaking
water. Your flax would soak so it will be ready and then
it would have to be removed and it would have to be
done in a certain period of time or it would go to
waste. וכל דבר שאבד *vechol davar she'avad* or any type you hire
these people for any type of a thing that if they don't
do it, it's going to be lost. Now the flax we understand,
if you don't do the flax in time it'll get ruined. But
how about the issue about the כלה *kalah* and the מת *met*?
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says, right, so if you look at תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos*, פריפרין *priparin*, תוספות *Tosafos* says דבר האבוד חשיב ליה שעתה
זמנו הוא לעשות *davar ha'avud chashiv lei sha'atah zmano hu
la'asot*. Now is the time to be done. If you don't get
it done now you're going to have the wedding without the band,
you're going to have the wedding without the חופה *chuppah*. So it's
true there's not actual some dollar and cents loss, it's not like
your bank account now is worth less, your net worth is less,
but nevertheless that's a loss for you. This is something that was
necessary now and you're going to be losing this service that you
needed done דווקא *davka* at this time.
He says it's the word for an אפיריון *apiryon*. אפיריון *apiryon* is
a bier so it could be used also to carry the...
oh maybe that's true. Okay, alright. So right, it's not necessarily the
חופה *chuppah*, right, it could also be the thing that you use
to carry the כלה *kalah* or to carry the מת *met*. Right,
correct. Thank you for that. Okay, so וכל דבר שאבד *vechol davar
she'avad*. Okay, so you hire them to do something that was necessary
to be done and it could not be delayed. וחזרו בהן *vichazru
bahen* and then they changed their mind. מקום שאין *makom she'ein*... שם
אדם *sham adam*, if there’s no other person to hire in their
place, שוכר עליהן *socher aleihen*, then you basically hire, then you, it’s
funny, there’s nobody else to hire, so hire somebody else. So the
שוכר עליהן *socher aleihen* means that you would have to hire somebody
else even at a very high rate, okay, and the word עליהן
*aleihen* means that you would get them to pay for it, alright?
So you can do that. So yeah, apparently you have a right
to get it in court, to sue them to pay for it,
alright. שוכר עליהן *socher aleihen* או מטען *o mat'an*, or you, or
you deceive them. You basically say fine, I’ll double, I’ll double your
fee, and they say okay, that will do it. And then after
they do it, you say I lied, okay? You were about to
back out on something that was a דבר האבד *davar ha'avad*, and
therefore I’m only going to pay you the fee we originally agreed
upon. So this idea that when they deceive one another there’s no
financial consequences is not always true. The first thing the משנה Mishna
*Mishna* tells you is if there is a דבר האבד *davar ha'avad*,
there are financial consequences. They would actually have to pay in order
to make sure that the job would get done, okay, or you
would at least be able to deceive them in order to make
sure that the job would get done. Alright, so that’s number one.
Now, number two. השוכר את האומנין *hasocher et ha'umnin* וחזרו בהם *vechazru
bahem*, now let's say it's not a דבר האבד *davar ha'avad*. You
hired them and then they quit, say, or they changed their minds,
so ידם על התחתונה *yadam al hatachtona*, they have the, their hand
is on their, you know, they have the lower hand, so you
know we have the phrase the upper hand, they have the lower
hand. אם בעל הבית baal habayit חוזר בו *im ba'al habayit chozer
bo*, I know, I’ll tell you in a minute. אם בעל הבית
baal habayit חוזר בו ידו על התחתונה *im ba'al habayit chozer bo
yado al hatachtona*, or if the owner, if the person who was
doing the hiring, he was the one that retracted, his, he has
the lower hand. Now what does the lower hand mean? So רש"י
*Rashi* basically says let’s see what both cases. So basically let’s say
I hired these workers to do a job for, you know, for
two dollars and they did half the job, okay, so and then
they want to back out. So if the, if the, you know,
the rate still is going for two dollars a day or you
know for two dollars for the job, so then they can back
out without consequences. That’s no ידם על התחתונה *yadam al hatachtona*. I
give them a dollar for the work they did, I take the
remaining dollar and I hire workers to do the rest of it.
Of course that assumes that other workers are available in the middle
of the day, which they might not, might not be. But let’s
say either because other workers are, let’s say that now the rates
have gone up by the middle of the day and now it’s
going to cost me a dollar and a half to finish the
job. So therefore I only pay them a half a dollar for
their work so that I can then use a dollar and a
half to get the work done, so that my whole expense will
be the two dollars that we originally contracted it. Now that all
works as long as the amount that’s coming to them is enough
to cover my losses, you know, in terms of hiring for the
rest of the job. If it’s not enough to cover my losses,
then you know I have limited recourse. Okay, but that’s at least
basic ידו על התחתונה *yado al hatachtona*, which is that if it’s
going to cost me more to finish the job, I can withhold
their, their, you know, their fee, I can withhold the amount that
they’ve earned so far in order to cover the losses to hire
the rest. Okay, now presumably that would also be, I’m, I, you
know, if even if the standard rate hasn’t changed, if to hire
somebody midday is going to cost me, you know, the rest. Although
I don’t know the answer to that. If it’s not a דבר
האבד *davar ha'avad*, maybe I have to wait till tomorrow. Do I
have the right to hire somebody in midday, should I wait till
tomorrow? It's not exactly clear to me. But the basic point is
that if they, if they back out, I can withhold their wages
to the point to cover any losses, you know, in terms of
the additional expense it'll cost me to cover to get the job
done. One minute, that's the case if they back out. If the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis *ba'al habayit* backs out, what's a case of
ידו על התחתונה *yado al hatachtona*? So that’s a case of let’s
say I hired them now for, let me just double-check רש"י *Rashi*
about this.
Right.
Right. So let’s say I hired them for three dol-
hold on, let me just read this one more time. ידם על
התחתונה שהוזלה מלאכת פועלים *yadam al hatachtona shehozla melachet poalim*, כל כוחו
יתן להם כמה שפסקו *kol kocho yiten lahem kama
shepasku*. It's not such a ידו על התחתונה *yado al hatachtona*.
Yeah, I mean רש"י's *Rashi's* scenario is not a huge ידו על
התחתונה *yado al hatachtona*. I hired them for three dollars for the-
for the job, they quit in the middle, and now actually the
rates are going at two dollars for the job. So the חידוש
chiddush *chiddush* is that I still pay them, not such a חידוש
*chiddush*, I pay them the dollar and a half, I backed out,
did I say they did, I backed out, okay, they did half
the job, we agreed at three dollars, but now the rates are
going at two dollars for the job. So nevertheless since they did
half the job, I still pay them a dollar and a half
for what they did even though, you know, now I could get
the job done at two dollars and their half of the work
is worth one dollar. That’s not such a big חידוש *chiddush*. We
contracted it at three dollars, I backed out, so I pay them.
Yeah. So anyway, that’s not such a חידוש *chiddush*, but anyway, that’s
רש"י's *Rashi's* scenario of ידו על התחתונה *yado
al hatachtona* for when the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis?
*ba'al habayit*. Now David had a question first.
Yeah. Right, doesn't seem to be. Right. That's the point that I
was making, that this משנה Mishna is very is very like ironic.
It says there's only complaints, there's no other consequences, and then it
gives all these financial consequences. So it is missing the keyword כיצד,
keitzad, right, so it does not seem like these are illustrations of
the first case. It seems like these are different cases than the
first case. So what's of course missing then is: so what is
the first case when it's deception that has no financial consequences? So
we don't know yet, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara.
yet. You know in the way back then, let's say, you know,
you could have hired two tiers of workers, those that go for
a dollar and a half and three dollars. So you know, you
want someone to do the whole job. You hired the
three dollars person and they back down in the middle. Can you
not say, "All right, I could have hired somebody, you know, at
a lower wage to do the whole job, and I'm going to
pay you less now, even for the work you already
did?"
I'm not understanding. They backed out,
so...
Forget about how, you know, like in other words your case, the
first case was, "Oh I have to hire someone for more money,
therefore I can take it out of their..." you know. But could
I say, "I always could have hired these cheaper workers, but I
like, you know, you do better work, but you know, so that's
why I hired you. But now you finished half a job, and
it's like you did nothing for me. I'm going only pay you
the dollar and a half, which I could have found somebody else."
Well, it's an interesting question. I mean, I would reframe that as
if they backed out and now you're going to have to get
somebody who's going to do a job of inferior quality, then I
imagine that you can pay them at the rate of the person
of inferior quality because the job as a whole will only be
done in inferior quality. So I imagine that something like that would
be correct.
And
also
no, we can't draw yet, Charlie.
I'm trying to fit this into our usual system of employment at
will on both sides, where I can quit my job with basically
no notice, unless I have a contract otherwise. And the employer can
fire you for no reason.
Right, so we're going to see about all of that, okay? Because
that's going to be, that might be a part of the idea
of the beginning part of the משנה. Mishna? It might depend on
the circumstances. So that's exactly what we're going to see, okay? The
opening of the משנה Mishna made it sound exactly like that, that
you could sort of quit or back out without consequence. And then
it says, no, there actually are consequences. So we'll take to see
how this plays out in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. כל המשנה ידו
על התחתונה. Kol hamishaneh yado al hatachtona. Now here's another הלכה halacha
which says, well yes, but this means something else. This means that
you don't do what you were hired to do. This goes back
to a classic משנה mishna, בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, you hired somebody
to dye your wool blue, and they dyed it red, or whatever
it was.
So therefore in that case, you pay them only the lesser of
their expenses or the amount the wool improved, not their normal fee,
okay? וכל החוזר בו ידו על התחתונה. Vechol hachozeir bo yado al
hatachtona. Now
that actually seems to be an illustration of the cases we dealt
with, which is whoever backs out, they have the lower hand. That
was the cases we dealt with, but again, what does that have
to do, what's the first case now in the משנה? mishna That's
really what's left to be explained. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara Okay. חזרו זה בזה לא קתני. Chazru zeh bazeh
lo katani. So what is this case of deceiving one another? So
the first point the משנה Mishnah says is חזרו זה בזה לא
קתני. Chazru zeh bazeh lo katani. It does not say that they
backed out, which is the next scenarios, אלא הטעו זה את זה.
ela hitu zeh et zeh. They deceived one another. So it sounds
like number one we're dealing with a different case than the others,
okay? It's not a case of backing out. It's something of deception
that's not about backing out. Okay. הטעו זה את זה. Hitu zeh
et zeh. דאתו פועלים אהדדי. de'atu poalim ahadadi. Now
because it's not about backing out, the גמרא Gemara assumes, therefore what
would be a case of deception? So the גמרא gemara has a
very interesting read. זה את זה does not mean the owners deceived,
you know, the employer deceived the employees. It means דאתו פועלים אהדדי,
de'atu poalim ahadadi,
that the workers deceived one another. השוכר את האומנים, Hasocher et ha'umanim,
right, the thing that's in plural. I mean, you hired workers והטעו,
they, the workers, deceived one another. So what's a case that the
workers deceived one another? דאתו פועלים... De'atu poalim... eventually we're going to
circle back and say, no, no, it does mean the בעל הבית
ba'al habayis deceived the workers or the workers deceived the employer, okay?
And maybe it even does mean they backed out and we'll figure
out another read. But for a while we're going to focus on
the possibility here that it's the workers deceived one another. Now why
is that your business? Because here's the point. You were hired basically
like a manager, and he deceived the other workers. So let's take
a look. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? דאמר ליה בעל הבית. de'amar lei
baal habayit. The בעל הבית ba'al habayis. hires one guy, he's going
to be the foreman, and he says to him: זיל אוגר לי
פועלים. Zil ogar li poalim. Go hire workers, okay? We've got this
job to be done, building my house. I'm paying you the foreman.
You go ahead, you hire the workers. Subcontracting. There you go. Exactly.
ואזל איהו ואטענהו. Ve'azal ihu ve'at'inhu. And then the foreman went and
he deceived the workers. So they just pocketed or something like that.
So we'll see what the specific is. In that case, there's no
financial consequence, they just have complaints. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Now what's
the case? אי דאמר ליה בעל הבית בארבעה. Ee de'amar lei baal
habayit be'arba'ah. Go hire them at four dollars a day. ואזל איהו
ואמר להו בתלתא Ve'azal ihu ve'amar lehu bitlata and he goes and
he hires them at three dollars a day. So תרעומת מאי עבידתיה?
taromet mai avidteih? Why do they have any basis for complaint, okay,
the
workers? סברו וקבילו. Savru vekabilu. They judged it and they accepted the
terms. So just because the owner was willing to give them four
dollars a day... I offered you three, you said yes, what type
of a complaint do you have? There was no deception, there was
no nothing. Okay. סבר וקביל. savar vekabil. אי דאמר ליה בעל הבית
בתלתא. i damar lei ba'al habayis bitlasa. Now let's say the owner
goes and says hire them at $3 a day. ואזל איהו ואמר
להו בארבעה ve'azel ihu ve'amar lehu be'arba'ah and he goes and he
says I'll pay you $4 a day. And then when it comes
time to get your pay, says oh I lied it was only
$3 a day. So היכי דמי. heichi dami. So and then says
that they just have a complaint they don't have any recourse. So
it says well what's the case exactly? אי דאמר להו שכרכם עלי.
i damar lehu scharkhem alai. If he says I'm hiring you at
$4 a day and I'm responsible
to pay your salary. The owner will pay me back, I'm responsible
to pay your salary. If that's true, נתיב להו מדידיה. nasiv lehu
midideih. So he has to give them the $4 a day. You
contracted and you are now conducting yourself as the obligated party to
pay. So you might only be able to get your $3 from
the owner but you've made a responsibility an obligation to them to
pay them $4. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. השוכר
את הפועל לעשות בשלו והראהו בשל חברו. hasocher es hapo'el la'asos beshelo
veher'eihu beshel chaveiro. I go and I say hey Michael you want
to come mow my lawn 20 bucks and then I show and
then I show him Gloria's lawn. I tell him that's my lawn
go mow it. Okay so who pays Michael in that case? So
נותן לו שכרו משלם. nosin lo scharo mishalam. I give him the
full pay וחזר ונוטל מבעל הבית מה שנהנה. vechozer venotel miba'al habayis
mah shenehneh. So I go ahead and I agree to pay Michael
20 bucks. I give Michael the 20 bucks. Then I go over
to Gloria מה שנהנה. mah shenehneh. However much Gloria benefited. So if
the normal cost of mowing the lawn is $10 and I overpaid
Michael, I give Michael $20 and I can get $10 from Gloria.
Gloria never hired him but Gloria did get a benefit from it.
So what Gloria has to do is she has to pay me
for the benefit that she received. Now it raises an interesting question
which is obligated? Yes yes this is a principle this is a
classic principle we've had before like ירד לתוך שדה חברו שלא ברשות.
yarad lesoch sdei chaveiro shelo birshus. I go into somebody's field without
any permission I go ahead and I improve it. That person does
not have to pay me what a normal fee would cost to
do it because they never made a contractual obligation to me but
they did receive benefit so they have to pay me for benefit.
Now it raises interesting questions which is let's say Gloria is the
type of person that she's happy to have her lawn be overgrown
and never mows it or whatever. There are people like that. Not
you Gloria we know but some people are like that anyway. So
is that considered like a benefit? Who gets to measure a benefit?
Maybe it's true maybe the property value went up maybe whatever. So
that's an interesting question but we're going to bracket that for now.
We're going to assume that there is a clear dollar value benefit
that Gloria received but it is not necessarily how much the thing
the value has improved or whatever is not necessarily how much the
contract was with Michael, how much we pay the worker. Okay so
that's for me to work out with Gloria but I made a
contract with Michael I owe Michael the money. Okay. Can I get
reimbursed because Gloria benefited from it? Yes and we'll figure out how
much that benefit is and how much she pays me back. So
in this case if I go ahead and I'm the foreman and
I basically hire the workers to work on the בעל הבית's ba'al
habayis yard but I say I will owe you the money I'll
pay you for that personally okay so then in that case I
have to pay them the four. I said I would pay them
the four. How much can I get reimbursed from the בעל הבית?
ba'al habayis Probably certainly no more than three. I mean assuming he
told me three because three would be a standard going rate. Okay.
So that anyway but in that case who has any complaints? The
workers collect from me what I contracted with them and I'll collect
from the בעל הבית ba'al habayis when I'm entitled to collect from
the בעל הבית. ba'al habayis Okay. So והראהו בשל חברו נותן לו
שכרו משלם וחזר ונוטל מבעל הבית מה שנהנה. veher'eihu beshel chaveiro nosin
lo scharo mishalam vechozer venotel miba'al habayis mah shenehneh.
So therefore if the בעל הבית ba'al habayis told me three and
I told them four they're not going to have any complaint. I'm
going to be obligated to pay them four. So לא צריכא lo
tzricha you need it for the following case. דאמר להו שכרכם על
בעל הבית. diamar lehu scharkhem al ba'al habayis. He says hey I'm
just a worker here just like you guys. I was told to
go hire you. I'm not going to pay you. The בעל הבית
ba'al habayis asked me to hire you for him. He is going
to pay you to work for today. Everybody gets $4 a day.
Who wants a job? Okay. So I've never undertaken a obligation to
them. I've
misrepresented the בעל הבית Baal Habayis represented him
incorrectly and now the question is how much does the בעל הבית
Baal Habayis, owe the workers? Okay so in that case
so the גמרא gemara says so ונחזי פועלין היכי מתגרי. venichzi po'alin
heichi misgarei.
So the גמרא gemara says okay but let's see what the going
rate of workers are. So if there's that misrepresentation I said four
but the בעל הבית Baal Habayis, only asked me three presumably the
גמרא Gemara says maybe if all workers are going for four maybe
that sort of maybe the בעל הבית Baal Habayis, does have to
pay them four because that's the standard going rate they were working
for him. Okay now it raises interesting questions because he never made
a contractual obligation with them what exactly sort of
defined that response. But that becomes an issue like if it's known
that I need a job done before I discussed יורד לתוך שדה
חברו שלא ברשות. yored lesoch sdei chaveiro shelo birshus. You come and
you mow my lawn and without any permission and it was a
case where I wasn't looking to have the lawn mown. looking to
get my lawn mowed. What would happen if everybody, if I am
looking to get my lawn mowed and you're an enterprising young man
and you go ahead there, Eytan, and you try to make a
little bit of money on the side to supplement your ישיבה Yeshiva
stipend, okay, and you go ahead and you know that I'm looking
for it, so you don't ask me if you'd like me to
mow your, if you'd like to mow your, if I'd like you
to mow my lawn, you just mow the lawn. And you say,
well, you know, pay me because that's the going rate and you
needed it done. So anyway, the reality is that there might be
something to that, that if it's known that I actually need the
job done and you do it even without an explicit contract, that
might create a quasi type of a contract just there. The implicit
sense that I needed it done might create, I needed it done
now, I need, yeah, exactly. So anyway, so here the גמרא Gemara
basically is saying that even if the בעל הבית Baal Habayis only
wanted to pay three, let's just see what the going rate is.
He clearly needed it done. If the going rate was four, maybe
he would be responsible. One minute, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says: והיכי דמי והיכי מתגרי. v'heichi dami v'heichi misgaray. So the
גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא דאיכא דמתגר בארבע ואיכא דמתגר בתלתא. lo
tzericha d'ika d'misgar b'arba v'ika d'misgar b'tlata.
So here now there are different people, you know, some people, you
know, some people are going for four, some people are going for
three, right? So, you know, so in that type of a case
you can't say, well the fact that they worked, if that's the
going rate four, they're obligated four. No, there are those and there
are those. So in that type of a case, I only wanted
to hire three, he told them four. How much is my responsibility
to them? One minute, so the גמרא Gemara says: דאמרו ליה, d'amru
lei, they say to him, here's their complaint. He says, they, the
workers, no, the workers now say to the בעל הבית, Baal Habayis,
no, the בעל הבית, Baal Habayis, or it could be the foreman,
I guess the foreman, because it says there זה על זה. zeh
al zeh. Anyway, but the point is, they're only going to get
three because I only agreed, the בעל הבית, Baal Habayis to pay
three. But their complaint is: דאמרו ליה, d'amru lei, A, you told
us four, and B, אי לאו דאמרת לן בארבע טרחינן ומתגרינן בארבע.
ei lav d'amrat lan b'arba tarchinan u'misgarinan b'arba. That they basically said,
you know, had you not told us four, we would have waited
to get the job from the guy who was offering four. He
can say to us, hey, you know, what skin is it off
your back? You know, people that's the rate, three, that's all you
would have gotten anyway, so don't complain. No, we do have a
complaint. They have a complaint that is basically saying you deceived us
because we would have waited to get a job that would have
paid us four. But the בעל הבית Baal Habayis is not responsible
for because he said three and there are workers that are available
at three. Okay, so in that case, it's they have a complaint,
but nobody can have any recourse. Which to me is pretty interesting,
right? Because it gets to the question of like, if I were
a בעל הבית, Baal Habayis you know, why wouldn't I basically do
this all the time? I go ahead and I have Michael be
my foreman. I say, Michael, go hire workers at three, and I
give him a wink, okay? And he knows that there are those
who go three or four. He goes and he basically tells everybody
four. Okay, I guess the point is, after a while people start
to learn better. Okay, but you always get the unsuspecting people, right?
So you go ahead and you tell them four, and I got
my guys working at three, and I got people, maybe the better
people to come, I got people whatever, right? So it raises interesting
questions of like, you know, what's the, what's their protection of the
innocent workers? Maybe they need to say to Michael, you know, prove
to us the בעל הבית, Baal Habayis it's not clear, right? Because,
you know, I guess that like many things, it's all, you know,
your basically reputation will have some impact. Yeah, though you had a
question?
The relationship between the בעל הבית Baal Habayis and the foreman is
not clear. Like, why isn't this foreman essentially a שליח? shaliach? And
we've seen סוגיות sugyos in בבא קמא Bava Kamma in which a
שליח shaliach has a certain amount of latitude, in other words, to
to make decisions with some independence.
Yeah, but you did, he said
he's not a שליח shaliach though, right? He's just, שליחות? shlichus?
Well, שליחות shlichus is a funny idea here and it raises a
good question. Like, what שליחות shlichus normally is, like, like to be
a שליח shaliach you can be a שליח shaliach to buy something
or to sell something. Can you be a שליח shaliach to actually
enter into like a contractual obligation in which you mismanaged,
well, no, it's because you didn't do what the, because you didn't
do what the בעל הבית Baal Habayis. said. So that's why it
doesn't, but if basically if a בעל הבית ba'al habayis said three
and he said three and they went and did it, it becomes
presumably
that a binding obligation. But is it a binding obligation because it's
at the end of the day it's just the רצון ratzon of
the בעל הבית ba'al habayis and they basically came and they worked,
or was there actually some sense of entering into a contract that
he did to represent? You know, normally that type of a thing
is less, so
that's something I think we're going to have to like put a
peg in and you know and think about because normally like when
you represent somebody's interest but you're not doing a particular concrete act
like buying or selling or whatever, you know, normally you need something
not שליחות shlichus but something more like an אדרכתא adrachta power of
attorney or so on. שליחות shlichus is not normally for like, go
enter into a contract for this to be my שליח. shaliach. Right,
you need more like of a power of attorney. So it's not
exactly clear in this case exactly what creates the contract, okay? It
might more be the דעת da'as of the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
and he's more just letting people know this is the דעת da'as
of the בעל הבית. ba'al habayis It's a very important question that
I think we're not going to fully answer right now.
Okay, so that's the case of the השוכר את הפועלים והטעו
זה את זה,
hasocher es hapoalim
v'hitu
zeh es zeh, which is the person who was supposed to hire
the workers misled. and told them a higher price and they can
only get from the בעל הבית ba'al habayis the lower rate if
there are multiple rates that are going that are going there okay
be the objective reality that they worked for the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis right if it was if you know sort of creates whatever
you know creates that obligation but it would not be beyond the
you know would not be beyond what the what
what one minute so in the case where right I mean take
the objective reality if basically everybody is going for four then even
if the בעל הבית ba'al habayis only said three he would still
have to pay them four and that's an important principle right because
that is like a case of יורד לתוך שדה חברו yored l'toch
s'deh chaveiro but you still pay what you benefit and if if
this is what everybody is going for so you benefited at the
cost of four dollars a day even if you only wanted to
pay three you would have to pay four but if people are
going at four and at three and the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
so the benefit could be rate could be rated at three dollars
a day and the בעל הבית ba'al habayis only wanted to pay
three dollars a day he doesn't have to pay more just because
this guy promised them more that's not his responsibility and they just
have a complaint okay so that's explanation one number one איבעית אימא
Iba'is eima and if you want you could say הכא בבעל הבית
עסקינן hacha b'ba'al habayis askinan now the בעל הבית baal habayit here
means that you hired somebody who normally was a homeowner himself who
normally could have spent the day working on his own field you
know come you know he come press my grapes in my you
know in in this person's yard no no no I have my
own grapes to press okay but I'll pay you more to come
with me so he actually was leaving his own work okay to
come do this other work
so הכא בבעל הבית עסקינן hacha b'ba'al habayis askinan
where I lost my place ah דאמרו ליה אי לאו דאמרת לן
בארבע הוה
זילא בן מילתא לאתגורי d'amru lei i lav d'amart lan b'arba hava
zila ban milsa l'isgurei so again we're getting back to the question
of what's the complaint so the point here is everybody is going
for you know everybody is going for three so what's their complaint
yeah I told you four but come on everybody is going for
three so before we said their complaint was that you know that
they could have hired themselves out at four if they hustled a
little bit and they worked hard and they said we would have
waited till four here the scenario is no everybody's going for three
but the complaint is I wouldn't have left my own work in
my own field to work for somebody else at the rate of
three I'm not a hired hand I own my own plot of
land you promised me more I figured I'd make a little profit
I went okay but that's so that's my complaint but at the
end of the day the בעל הבית baal habayit from his side
only agreed to pay three and only benefited three so he only
pays three so even though the foreman promised four okay this guy
only gets three because that's only that's what the
בעל הבית baal habayit benefited but what the employer only pays three
because that's what he benefited even though the foreman promised four but
the employer only intended three and only benefited three and the employee
has the complaint that I would never have left working in my
own land on my own plot of land to help you for
the normal going rate yeah
get the foreman let's say you and I just you told me
before and we know that everyone goes for three yeah you yourself
told me
then you pay me four sure yeah then you contracted it at
four okay איבעית Iba'is so that's explanation number two why there's a
complaint not because people are going at four and three but I
personally would never have agreed to anything more than four anything less
than four okay yes
we're using the word deceit but we're not considering that anybody's lying
right it's just in other words the well
the foreman's lying no
but but what I mean is when they come to him and
say that he's he's going to say what he actually said to
them
he's not going to lie
and say no I said three
oh yeah the deception was at the time not when they come
to
court okay איבעית אימא Iba'is eima if you want you could say
לעולם בפועלים עסקינן l'olam b'poalim askinan we're again dealing with them hiring
workers and promising them four when the rate is three so what's
the complaint because the גמרא Gemara would say well you don't even
have meaning the point of the גמרא Gemara is if everybody is
going for three even though I promised you four you don't even
have really a right to complain you know you you know big
deal I promised you more at the end of the day you
got what everybody got what's your complaint so it's important to know
the גמרא Gemara sees scenarios where the guy owns his own plot
of land or some people were going for four it's to say
why it's justified to even have a basis to complain okay because
if everybody was going for three and you had no reason to
expect more and I promised you four you don't even have and
the end of the day it was three you don't even have
a right to complain alright so that's interesting like there's a threshold
for legitimate complaint so the scenario number three where it's a legitimate
complaint is דאמרי ליה כיון דאמרת לן בארבע טרחינן ועבדינן לך עבידתא
שפירתא d'amri lei kivan d'amart lan b'arba tarchinan v'avidnan lach avidsa shapirta
no no no because you said four we worked extra hard we
did a really good job for you okay and that's why you
know you should be paying us four and if you don't pay
us four we really have a good complaint it's true the normal
rate is three but we worked extra hard and now you're only
going to get you know because you said four now here's an
important question though if they really did work extra hard remember we
get back to the point that if objectively speaking the בעל הבית
baal habayit got that benefit he has to pay them for it
so if you go look and you say psh psh you know
I had you mow the lawn but you did all the corners
so nicely and you trimmed it here whatever you know is not
a twenty-dollar job, that's a thirty-dollar job, right? So if that's really
objectively, exactly, if that's really objectively what happened, then the בעל הבית
baal habayit is obligated to pay them for it, even though he
only intended three, right? But his foreman said four and they came
and they did a four-dollar job, they did a special job.
So in that case, but if the foreman said three consistently,
they could come back and say? No, that's not true. No. Why?
But if somebody offers me to go do the lawn? Yeah, that's
a little ironic, but at the end of the day, if you
contracted for three, you contracted for three. Okay, here the point sort
of was that there was sort of like an absence of a
contract. So we look more at the objectively what happened.
So in this type of a case, in this case, okay, so,
in this case,
the point is that maybe actually the foreman told them four, they
did a four-dollar job, even if everybody goes for three, they did
a four-dollar job, so maybe actually he should pay them. So what's
the scenario that they have a, that they can legitimately claim they
did an extra job, but the בעל הבית baal habayit doesn't have
to pay them for it? So the case is you can't, you
cannot see the work that they've done. What's the case? Let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says ולחזי עבידתא, velechezi avidta, let's
go check out the work, and if it's actually true that they
did extra, and they did extra good, he would have to pay
them. So the גמרא Gemara says בירסקא. beriska. No, it's a case
of digging a furrow. So the גמרא Gemara says ריסקא נמי מידיע
ידא. riska nami midaya yada. So go look at the furrow, see
if it was a nice furrow or not. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, דמלי מיא ולא ידיע. demali maya velo yediya. No, by
now it's filled with water, so there's no way of assessing, okay,
so there's no way of assessing. The בעל הבית ba'al habayis says
I only promised three, you know, the standard workers were going for
three. So they have a complaint, they said we did an extra
good job because we were told four. I'm sorry, there's no way
of assessing that, like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya.
I never said four, so you have a complaint that you were
promised four, it's a complaint, go complain to the guy who said
it, but there's no economic recourse. So back to what we said,
there if there is a case, what is the case where they
have a legitimate complaint but no economic recourse? So we gave three
scenarios, okay. The basic scenarios were, all of them were that they
were hired at four, but the going rate was three.
If actually the reality was was that the go, they were, you
know, that the going rate was four, but the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis intended less, or the going rate was three but they did
a job worth four, then they actually would get paid four, because
then you have to just pay them the benefit you received. But
the scenario is no, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis only received a
benefit of three, the going rate was three, but they had a
reason to say that they were told four and and legitimately could
have expected four, either because they could have hustled more and gotten
four, or because they were, they would have stayed and worked on
their own field, or because they said they did an extra good
job but there's no way of assessing it. In all those cases,
those claims give them a good reason to register a complaint. Like,
you know, it's sort of, I'm trying to think what is תרעומת
taromet mean, but now it just occurs to me, sort of like,
sort of like a complaint with the Better Business Bureau, right? So,
but it means to a certain threshold. So in all those cases
it hits the threshold of a legitimate complaint, but not enough for
financial recourse. Okay, but if basically, you know, you only would have
gotten three anyway, okay, so the guy lied to you, but you
only would have gotten three, you only did a job worth three,
you don't even have a basis for a complaint, okay, so that
would be cases where it's even, falls below that threshold. Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara discuss our mechanism for determining the going rate?
Like it seems like...
Yeah, so you know somebody told this to me a while ago
which is is that, you know he said like in in cases
of like, you know, real law, you know adjudicated like secular law
or whatever he says, at least, you know half of the effort
is not in determining what the law is but in determining what
are the standards of assessing the facts. Right? And in the גמרא
Gemara you basically like almost never have that being addressed. And does
it have to do with the fact that, you know, so often
it's theoretical, it was only like rarely actually applicable? But the basic
answer is like no. I mean it's a great question. How do
you determine what the going rate is? You know all those types
of things, right? The assessing of facts is never really, you know,
elaborated on. I'm sorry, I misunderstood this.
So so back to where we just were. You said if you
just go and mow the lawn and do a four-dollar job, you
get four dollars. Right. And you know, and in this case but
so if I contracted you for three, you and I, and then
you do like a four-dollar job, I
still just pay the three because we talked... I think so, meaning
I think so, I mean I imagine that if you did something
extra which is concretely extra that you could say wasn't part of
the contract, you know, then that would then then you did something
in addition to the contract and the contract wouldn't, then presumably I
would have to pay you. But if it was just seen that
you did the contractual obligation but you did it in a better
way, you know, it's hard to exactly assess, I'm not exactly sure
what the case would be there. But it might be depending on
whether you sort of see this as an addition or just did
a better job of what we contracted. But if it was only
the job that we contracted, even if you did it in a
nicer way, at the end of the day we agreed on a
price. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, איבעית אימא,
iba'it eima, and if you want, לעולם דאמר ליה בעל הבית בארבעה,
le'olam de'amar lei baal habayit bearba'a, ואזל איהו אמר להו בתלתא. va'azal
ihu amar lehu betlata. Going back to that, the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis. said four, he told them three. So what complaint do they
have? I mean, at the end of the day they agreed to
take three, so what So what if the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
was ready to pay them four? What's the complaint? סבור וקביל, savur
vekibbel, they assessed and they accepted the terms. דאמרי ליה, de'amri lei,
no, they can say to the foreman, לית לך, leis lach, don't
you hold of the פסוק, pasuk, אל תמנע טוב מבעליו, al timna
tov mib'alav, do not withhold good from its owners? Like, you know,
the rate was four, we worked a hard day, so like we
have a real complaint that you underpaid, that you paid us—yes, in
the end we accepted it, we need to put food on the
table, but we have a legitimate complaint that the owner was prepared
to pay it and that was the going rate. So you did
a—you know, you did a bad turn by us. Alright, so that's
the complaint. You know, so it's interesting that even though—right, but even
though you willingly accepted the terms, right, the fact that somebody still,
like, didn't do right by you. Okay, now, the גמרא Gemara says
like this: פשיטא, pshita, אי אמר ליה בעל הבית בתלתא ואזל איהו
ואמר בארבע. ei amar lei ba'al habayis betlasa ve'azal ihu ve'amar be'arba.
Now, now we're going to have another variation of this question. Eventually
we're going to get back to explaining פשט pshat in the משנה,
Mishnah okay, but now the פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah is
this case with the foreman. Now we want to raise the following
question. He says—the בעל הבית ba'al habayis says, go hire them at
three, and he went and he hired them at four. ואמרי ליה,
ve'amri lei, and they said to him, כמו שאמר בעל הבית. kemo
she'amar ba'al habayis. Okay, we'll agree because just as the בעל הבית
ba'al habayis has said. Meaning, we're assuming that you are accurately representing
the דעת da'as of the בעל הבית. ba'al habayis Now the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis said three and he said four. So when they
said like the בעל הבית ba'al habayis said, they didn't mean to
undersell themselves. They didn't mean to say, "oh, the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis said three, we're only going to do three." Right? So גמרא
Gemara says it's obvious in that case, פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious in
that case where אמר ליה בעל הבית בתלתא ואזל איהו ואמר בארבע
ואמרי כמו שאמר בעל הבית דטפי איילויי, amar lei ba'al habayis betlasa
ve'azal ihu ve'amar be'arba ve'amri kemo she'amar ba'al habayis detfei iyluyei, that
their intention is the higher one. We mean we believe you that
that's what the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is saying, meaning we believe
the בעל הבית ba'al habayis did not say more than that or
something. You know, but it doesn't mean that we would want to
take less if the בעל הבית ba'al habayis said less. So in
a case where—like the cases we dealt with where that would matter—that
he said four, you know, and then they would—the fact—you know, they're
not agreeing to three. They're basically assuming just because they said, "we
believe—you know, we'll do like the בעל הבית ba'al habayis. says," we're
assuming that that says they're still intending four.
And since they're still
intending four, they have the basis for complaint or all the other
cases we dealt with. Okay, that was scenario... but not—just complaint, but
not to get more. Yeah, alright, unless again, unless workers are also
going for four, that would be a different case. Okay, אלא, ela,
but the point being that just because they said, "we'll do like
the בעל הבית ba'al habayis says" does not mean that they're underselling
themselves, okay, that they were—they're accepting less than the guy is representing.
But here's the interesting question. אלא, ela, אי אמר ליה בעל הבית
בארבע, ei amar lei ba'al habayis be'arba, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
says four, ואזל איהו ואמר להו בתלתא, ve'azal ihu ve'amar lehu betlasa,
and he said three, ואמרי, ve'amri, and they say, כמו שאמר בעל
הבית. kemo she'amar ba'al habayis. So they don't say, "we'll accept three."
They'll say, "okay, you know, or they do say, we'll accept it
based on what the—you know, because of—you know, just as the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis has said," believing that this guy is representing the
בעל הבית. ba'al habayis So maybe in that case they really contracted
for four because that's what the בעל הבית ba'al habayis says and
that's their intention there, for—is to say, not what you're saying, but
what you're saying as it represents what the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
says. So really we're only agreeing to what the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis? said. Okay. ואמרי כמו שאמר בעל הבית. ve'amri kemo she'amar ba'al
habayis. Right. מאי? mai? What do we say? אדיבורא דידיה קסמכי? adibura
didei kesamchi? So are they saying, "you're saying three and we trust
you that that's what the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is saying and
we're agreeing to three"? Okay. קסמכי. kesamchi. דאמרי ליה מהימנת לן, de'amri
lei meheimnas lan, you are trusted to us, דהכי אמר בעל הבית,
dehachi amar ba'al habayis, that's what the employer is saying. And therefore
when they say כמו שאמר בעל הבית, kemo she'amar ba'al habayis, they
mean just as you said, we're trusting that's what the בעל הבית
ba’al habayis says and we're agreeing to three. That's one scenario. או
דלמא, o dilma, or do we say, אדיבורא דבעל הבית קסמכי? adibura
deba'al habayis kesamchi? What they're actually saying is, we're not so sure
you're accurately representing it, so we will agree to be hired but
only based on what the בעל הבית ba’al habayis himself really said
and we'll find that out. Okay. If there happens to be a
difference between what he said and what you said, we're going based
on what he said. So when they say כמו שאמר בעל הבית,
kemo she'amar ba'al habayis, how do we interpret it? Do we interpret
it as, we trust that what you're saying represents the בעל הבית?
ba’al habayis Or do we say, not like you said, like the—you
know, if there's ever any question, we're going based on what the
בעל הבית ba’al habayis says? So how do you interpret their response?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear. הוי לי גיטי. hevei li gitti. So a woman says
to a messenger, "go bring me my גט." get. Okay, go to
my husband, he wants to divorce me, go deliver the גט. get.
Okay. And so makes him a שליח shaliach what's called a שליח
להולכה, shaliach leholacha, a שליח shaliach to deliver the גט get to
me, which also could be conceptualized as—there's an interesting question, can a
woman make a שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha or a woman only makes
a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabbala because all the woman could do is
receive it? So she could make a שליח shaliach to receive it,
and the husband makes a שליח shaliach to—you know, to bring the
גט. get. Okay. So, so this way what we'll assume for that's
the case for now. So anyway, so basically what the woman is
saying is a woman, you know, goes ahead and says, and says,
"go ahead, go to my husband and tell him..." I want you
him to send my גט get to me through you. So basically
present my present yourself to my husband as my you know as
his שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha that you would bring the גט get
to me. All right? So that's what the woman says. And then
he goes to the husband and he says, ואשתך אמרה, ve'ishtecha amra,
your wife told me התקבל לי גיטי, hitkabel li giti, accept her
גט get from you. Meaning be a שליח לקבלה. shaliach lekabala. The
difference being that by saying that that's his role, he doesn't have
to bring the גט get to the woman. He's representing the woman
at that moment and she's divorced immediately. So he is misrepresenting what
the wife said. והוא אומר, vehu omer, and the husband says, הילך
כמה שאמרה, heilech kemah she'amra, here take this גט get just like
she said. Okay, so it's a perfect case, right? He misrepresents what
she says. Does that mean like you said and I'm trusting that's
what she said? Or does that mean no, like she really said
in case she said something different? So what's the הלכה? halacha? So
אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב, amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav, אפילו הגיע גט לידה אינה מגורשת.
afilu higi'a get leyada einah megoresheret. She's not divorced either way. She's
not divorced immediately and she's not divorced when the גט get is
delivered. Why? Because basically presumably what that means is I am trusting
the שליח shaliach that he is accurately representing. So therefore I'm only
treating him as a שליח לקבלה, shaliach lekabala, not a שליח להולכה.
shaliach leholacha. I'm not making him my שליח. shaliach. I'm believing that
he's her שליח. shaliach. So I give it to him. Okay, so
that didn't work because she didn't make him a שליח לקבלה. shaliach
lekabala. Now he goes and he delivers it to her. That doesn't
work because I didn't make him my שליח להולכה. shaliach leholacha. Okay?
So that's why she's not divorced either way. But the point being
that when I say take like she said, what I mean is
take like you're saying and I believe what you're saying is what
she said. Okay? And when it wasn't, then the whole thing falls
apart. Okay? So you see that when you say like the person
said, it means like you're saying and I trust what you're saying
is what they're saying. שמע מינה, shema mina, you see from this,
דדיבורא דידיה קסמיך, dadibura didey kasamich, that you rely on the words
of the person in front of you that those accurately represented it.
דאי סלקא דעתך דדיבורא דידה קסמיך, de'i salka datach dadibura didah kasamich,
if when the husband said what she said meant what she really
said, so מכיוון דמטא גט לידיה תתגרש, mikeivan demata get leyadei titgaresh,
so then he should be a שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha because he
should have basically said I will treat you like whatever my wife
really said, that's what I'm going to do. And the wife said
that he should be a delivery שליח, shaliach, so that should have
been what happened. So you see that that's not what happened. That
it means I trust you and he was lying, so nothing worked.
So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
הכי השתא, hachi hashta, you cannot compare that case to our case.
What type of a comparison is that? בשלמא אי אתמר איפכא, bishlama
i itmar ipcha, now the basic point of what רב אשי Rav
Ashi is going to say is the following. I'm just going to
jump to the end
so you can appreciate what he's going to say. That when the
guy says I'm a שליח לקבלה, shaliach lekabala, okay, that act is
basically read, forget whether what the husband believes or doesn't believe, that
act is basically read as I am rejecting my שליחות shlichus of
the wife because my שליחות shlichus from the wife would require me
to schlepp the גט get all the way back to her. What
I am saying is that I am prepared to be a שליח
לקבלה, shaliach lekabala, which takes more responsibility but makes it easier. But
the point is since what I represented was less work than what
she told me, we read that as that I basically am rejecting
the שליחות. shlichus. So what he's going to say is the reason
it didn't work in that case was not because the husband you
know wasn't synced with what the wife said or you know trusted
the שליח shaliach rather than the wife. It doesn't matter. The husband
could totally have said whatever the wife says I don't care what
you're saying, whatever my wife says that's what we're doing. But the
שליח shaliach by calling himself a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala was rejecting
his שליחות. shlichus. Okay? So that's why he says that case is
not relevant. So let's read what would have been a good example.
It would have been a good example would have been the reverse.
That the wife said be my שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala and he
said to the husband your wife asked me to be your שליח
להולכה, shaliach leholacha, your delivery שליח, shaliach, because then he's accepting more
responsibility. Okay, so that actually would have been an interesting question. Let's
take a look. הכי השתא, hachi hashta, בשלמא אי אתמר איפכא, bishlama
i itmar ipcha, it would have been good it would have been
said the opposite. התקבל לי גיטי, hitkabel li giti, she said to
the שליח shaliach receive my גט, get, and then he goes and
he says ואשתך אמרה, ve'ishtecha amra, your wife said to me הוי
לי גיטי, havi li giti, that I should be the delivery שליח
shaliach not the receiving שליח. shaliach. So he's accepting more responsibility. In
that case והוא אומר, vehu omer, and the husband says הילך כמה
שאמרה, heilech kemah she'amra, take it like she said. Okay, now that
would have been interesting to explore when the wife would have been
divorced. דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב, de'amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav, משיגיע גט לידה מגורשת. mishiagi'a
get leyada megoresheret. If the statement had been in that scenario, she'd
be מגורשת megoresheret as soon as the גט get was given in
the hands of the שליח. shaliach. So that was what the wife
said, be my שליח לקבלה. shaliach lekabala. Then we could have inferred
אלמא דדיבורא דידה קסמיך, almah dadibura didah kasamich, when he says like
she said it really means like she said and then it would
have been immediate. אינמי inami or if the פסק psak had been
the other way, משיגיע גט לידה מגורשת, mishiagi'a get leyada megoresheret, she's
divorced when the גט get gets delivered, אלמא almah then we would
have seen דדיבורא דידיה קסמיך, dadibura didey kasamich, when he says take
it like she said it means take it like you're saying and
I believe what you're saying is what she said. So that would
have been a great, we could have tested it, right, that he
would not have been actually rejecting the שליחות, shlichus, he would have
been accepting more potential responsibility. And then either she would have been
divorced right away or she would have been divorced when it got
delivered, based on whether he was trusting what he said or trusting
or or going by what she said. That would have been a
perfect way to test our question. Okay, but אלא התם ela hasam
but in the case that we were given, when he says I'm
receiving it and he was told to deliver it, משום דעקר שליח
משליחותיה לגמרי, mishum de’akar shliach mishlichusei legamrei, it's because he's completely uprooting
his שליחות shlichus דאמר ליה שליח לקבלה הוינא de’amar lei shliach lekabbalah
havina I'll only agree to accept it, שליח להולכה לא הוינא shliach
leholachah lo havina I refuse to be a שליח shliach to deliver
it. Okay, okay, so that is you can't
so that was a nice question, in the case of employment, they
said yes, we'll do it like the בעל הבית ba’al habayis says,
does that mean we'll do it like you say and we're trusting
it's what the בעל הבית ba’al habayis says, or does it mean
we'll do it what the בעל הבית ba'al habayit says and we're
not necessarily trusting what you're saying but it's what the בעל הבית
says. And we don't have an answer. The case by גט get
was an interesting example, but it does not provide us with an
answer. Yes.
I can't now I can't help but see that the גמרא Gemara
itself is making a comparison with the foreman's like a שליח shliach
and he was so over.
Yes, I mean it is making an
analogy, it is making an analogy, but again I don't think that
it is prove I don't think it proves the case because the
דוקא davka question is that when I, you know, whose word am
I trusting? So I don't think you know it necessarily means that
the foreman is playing as our שליח. shliach. It's true we're comparing
it to a case or שליח, shliach, but it's you know it's
by analogy. Basically somebody says something to me and I say like
so and so says, what does that mean? You know whose דעת
da’as am I going by? So it's not an exact it's possible,
I'm not denying it's possible that the foreman is a שליח, shliach,
but it doesn't prove it from this case.
Yes, he can be argued with the case of a גט, get,
like you know listen I know this guy's a sleazy guy who's
giving his wife a lot of trouble, I'm going to say שליח
לקבלה shliach lekabbalah so that in his mind he won't go back.
Right, I always intended on walking it over to her.
Yeah, fine, there's a lot of okay moving on. But yeah, there's
a lot of ways you could look at that. גמרא Gemara. says
like this, where are we? Okay, אי בעית אימא, ei bayis eima,
so now so we had a series of explanations of the משנה
Mishnah. where הטעו hitu that means the foreman is the workers tricked
one another, the foreman tricked the workers in cases where that led
to questions about what's a legitimate enough complaint that there's תרעומת, taroumes,
you know needs to reach a certain threshold that there's a legitimate
reason why they should have expected more but they don't get more
because they didn't benefit him more than he would have paid. Okay,
and then led to these questions about you know whose word do
they trust like you know who are they implicitly contracting with if
the foreman might be misrepresenting them. Now we go back to the
פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah and פשט pshat in the משנה
Mishnah we're going to say a simpler פשט, pshat, we're not talking
about the workers misleading, we're talking about the employer and the employees.
Okay, so אי בעית אימא. ei bayis eima.
Even though we've explained the פשט pshat a certain way, we haven't
the תרעומת taroumes thing actually makes sense the way the גמרא.
Gemara Right, but correct, but we are but as we're going to
see there's going to be a ברייתא braisa that's going to sort
of push us to say, and you know, and what it forces
us to do is introduce a whole other dynamic in the משנה.
Mishnah, Like the משנה Mishnah seems to be talking about employer-employee and
it sort of forces us to read in a whole separate type
of a scenario. So now we're going to suggest one that's in
a way simpler because it keeps with the standard dynamic in the
משנה Mishnah of the employer and the employees. So let's take a
look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי בעית אימא, ei bayis
eima, so if you want going back to פשט pshat in the
משנה, Mishnah האי תנא חזרו נמי הטעו קרי ליה. hai tanna chazru
nami hitu kari lei. Our תנא tanna when he says deceived, it's
another way of saying that they backed down. Now of course the
problem's going to be that why does it say there are no
financial consequences if afterwards the משנה Mishnah, says there are financial consequences
for backing out. So this is going to give us an opportunity
to quote a ברייתא braisa which is a very long ברייתא braisa
and gives a lot of specifics, okay, and that's going to illustrate
the משנה mishna and illustrate that some of the points of the
משנה mishna are a matter of debate. So let's take a look.
דתניא detanya we learn in a ברייתא, braisa, השוכר את האומנין והטעו
את בעל הבית או בעל הבית הטעה אותן. hasocher es ha’umnin vehitu
es ba’al habayis o ba’al habayis hita osan. So it starts with
the language of הטעה, hita, right, deceived. But notice it's explicit, it's
not that the workers deceived one another, the workers deceive the בעל
הבית or the בעל הבית deceives them. Okay, אין להם זה על
זה אלא תרעומת,
they only have a complaint. So there it seems very clear, right,
it's an elaboration of our משנה, mishna it says complaint, הטעו, hitu,
but it's between the workers and the employer. Okay, now what's the
case? Okay, במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim,
when is that true? שלא הלכו, shelo halchu, when they did not
actually show up yet to work. So meaning it's very clear from
the context that הטעה hita means they backed down. I hired you
to come to work for me to you know to go and
to you know to go over to ראובן Reuven and to collect
all of his wares and to bring them to me, okay, and
you told me before you got to work the next morning, by
the way I changed my mind I'm not showing up to work.
Or I called you and I said by the way I changed
my mind you're not don't come to work today you're not hired.
So that's the case of הטעה hita where there's no financial consequences.
So now it's very
clear. work began. And before the work began, the contact is not
yet binding. So that's a really important point. Until that point, it's
just
like an arrangement. It's not a contract. Okay, it's a plan. It
doesn't become a binding relationship until the work begins. So if you
back out at the last minute, even though I have a complaint,
like now I got to schlep around, I planned yesterday for the
work I'm going to do today. You tell me now at 6:00
AM that you're not to show up, you know, what am I
supposed to do?
And you turned down another job.
Well, exactly, exactly, exactly. Yes. So you only have a complaint and
nothing more if the change happened before the work began. And what
about expenses?
Because he had recruiting expenses. That's a right.
That's an You had equipment. All right, that's an interesting question. So
תוספות discusses that. I mean, that's also like a גרמא Gerama or
גרמי Garme type of a question. So תוספות discusses that a little
bit. Okay, yes. So anyway, we'll read the תוספות in a minute.
But those are all good questions. Hold off on that. Okay, so
the משנה mishna says like this: במה דברים אמורים שלא הלכו. Bamedvar
amurim shelo halchu. When they didn't show up yet to work, then
it's only complaints if you back out. אבל הלכו החמורים ולא מצאו
תבואה. Aval halchu hachamarim velo matzu tvua.
They went to pick up the grain. They were told go to
Reuven, get the grain, bring it to me. And they went and
Reuven said, I'm sorry, I don't have any grain to give you.
ופועלים ומצאו שדה כשהיא לחה. upoalim umatzu sade kesheehi lach.
Or the workers were coming to plow the field or whatever they
were, and then they found that the field was too moist and
it couldn't be plowed. Okay, so but they actually showed up. So
once you actually show up, נותן להם שכר משלם. noten lahem sechar
mishalam. You give their full pay. Okay, that's interest. Even if you
contract by the hour?
Like how would that?
Presumably though, even if you're paying by the hour, you know, it
seems like the assumption is it's a daily job. I'm not sure
about that. Let's let's read a little bit more. אבל אינו דומה
הבא טעון לבא ריקן. Aval eno dome haba taun leba rekan.
But it's not similar to somebody who has to schlep stuff to
somebody who has to come back to the city with an empty
wagon. עושה מלאכה ליושב ובטל. Oseh melacha leyoshev ubatel. Or somebody who
has to go and actually plow the field to sitting around and
doing nothing. This gets back to the standard idea of the גמרא
Gemara about פועל בטל, poel batel, which means I pay you for,
you know, for your lost work. I pay you for the fact
that you're not working today. But basically, if I would have said
to you, how much would you accept today to come to my
field and to sit around and do nothing? Okay, you're giving up
the $30 a day that you could get by plowing the field.
What would it take to come to my field and not plow
and just sit there for the day? Okay, so then you, oh,
that I would take 25. Okay, I mean, it's tough to put
food on the table. Okay, then I only pay you 25 because
you didn't actually plow, but that's what you would have accepted to
come and show up and do nothing. Okay, so that becomes then
I am obligated for the day. You know, Michael's question where it
says how much of the obligation is it, it is a presumption
here, I believe, that you're hiring them for the day, so you
pay them for the day. We're going to work with that assumption.
Okay, now, במה דברים אמורים, bamedvar amurim,
when is this true? שלא התחילו במלאכה. shelo hitchilu bemilacha. They didn't
begin the work. Okay, what could be worse? I mean, if you're
already paying them full, how is beginning the work going to be
different? Let's take a look. אלו התחילו במלאכה, Elu hitchilu bemilacha, but
if they began the work, שמין להם מה שעשו. shamin lahem ma
sheasu. Then you pay them for the work that they've done. כיצד,
Keitzad, what does that mean? קיבלו קמה לקצור בשני סלעים. Kiblu kama
liktzor bishnay sela'im. They agreed to cut all the grain for $2.
קיצרו חציה והניחו חציה. Kitzu chetzya vehinichu chetzya. They cut half and
they left half over. בגד לארוג בשני סלעים, Beged learog bishnay sela'im,
or to weave a garment for $2. ארגו חציה והניחו חציה, Argu
chetzya vehinichu chetzya, and they did half. שמין להם את מה שעשו.
Shamin lahem et ma sheasu. You assess, okay, how much did you
do? It was half. Here's a dollar. היה יפה ששה דינרין. Haya
yafe shisha dinarin. Now, let's say to do the other half would
have cost a dollar and a half. Okay, there are four dinar
per סלע. sela. It would have cost a dollar and a half
to finish. This is what we said earlier. נותן להם סלע. noten
lahem sela. You pay them either a half
dollar. I'm sorry. נותן להם סלע. noten lahem sela. Oh, I skipped
a line. Did I? ששה דינרין. shisha dinarin. נותן להם סלע. noten
lahem sela. So now you only give them a סלע. sela. או
יגמרו מלאכתן ויטלו שני סלעים. O yigmeru melachtan veyitlu shnay sela'im. Or
they
say
they finish and they get all two סלע. sela. So in that
case, even if, I'm sorry, the point is here, because even if
the it's going to cost me more now to get it done,
it's now going to cost me a dollar and a half to
get it done, whereas if they would have we contracted for $2.
Nevertheless, I still pay them the dollar they did. That's not what
our משנה Mishna said. Remember, our משנה Mishna said that I get
to hold back their wages to pay for
the extra expense. This is actually saying no. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to say that the author of this משנה Mishna actually
feels that the פועל, poel, the worker, always has the upper hand
and does not lose as a consequence of backing out in the
middle of the day, even if it's going to wind up costing
the בעל הבית more. ואם סלע נותן להם סלע. ve'im sela noten
lahem sela. And if it's worth a סלע, sela, and if it's
worth a סלע, sela, then he gives them a סלע. sela. Meaning
that if the remaining job is only worth a סלע, sela, then
he also pays them a סלע, sela, which is obvious. If the
remaining job is worth one and a half and he still pays.
then certainly if the remaining job is worth one he pays them
what he agreed. The גמרא Gemara will discuss that. רבי דוסא אומר
Rabbi Dosa omeir שמין להם מה שעתיד להיעשות. shamin lahem ma she'atid
le'hei'asos. No no no you assess how much is it going to
cost to get the job done. היה יפה ששה דינרין haya yafeh
shisha dinarin if it's going to cost a dollar and a half
to get the job done and you had agreed initially to two
dollars and they did half the job נותן להם שקל nosein lahem
shekel the שקל shekel is half a סלע sela then you only
give them a half dollar. או יגמרו מלאכתן ויטלו שני סלעים o
yigmeru melachtan ve'yitlu shenei sela'im but if they want to go ahead
and finish let them finish for the two that we agreed upon.
ואם סלע ve'im sela and if the remaining job is only a
dollar then obviously נותן להם סלע. nosein lahem sela. So the ברייתא
braita so our משנה Mishna was רבי דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. Okay so
basically here's a case where they backed out according to our משנה
Mishna
and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa I get to hold back from them
the money that now it's going to
extra expense and according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma he actually
says no they're entitled to back out in the middle of the
day without any consequences they get paid exactly how much that was
agreed upon. Now of course the question is going to be how
is this different than the first part? If they show up and
back out right it says once they showed up I pay them
full here it says that actually I don't pay them full. So
the one way of explaining the גמרא will explain the difference as
we'll see but the first easiest way of explaining the difference is
who backed out. Okay if I go ahead they show up and
I back out then I pay them their full job. Let's say
they show up and they back out okay then it didn't tell
me what the consequence was right it told me the consequence of
if I back out after they've showed up I pay full. If
they back out so then that's this part of it if they
back out then according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma they actually
are always protected even after they've shown up even after they've started
they can back out and not have to pay anything and not
have to lose anything and they get their proportional to what they
agreed on. And according to רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa no no if
they backed out I get to withhold from them the money that
this is going to cost me. Okay let's read a little bit
more and I know it's thirty but let's do one more minute.
במה דברים אמורים בדבר שאינו אבוד bamei devarim amurim be'davar she'eino avud
if it's not going to become a real loss. אבל בדבר האבוד
aval be'davar ha'avud is going back to our משנה שוכר עליהן או
מטען. socher aleihen o mat'an. You can actually hire workers and they
have to pay or you can deceive them. כיצד מטען keitzad mat'an
how do you deceive them? אומר להן omer lahen סלע קצתי לכם
sela katzati lachem yes it's true I promised to pay you a
dollar בואו וטלו שתים bo'u utelu shtayim I'll pay you two just
stay at work. And they would and then in the end you
only pay them one. עד כמה שוכר עליהן ad kamma socher aleihen
and how much can you go ahead and hire other workers and
make them have to pay for it? Again I don't know exactly
how you're going to get that in court I mean you don't
have their money in your hand you'll have to sue for it.
עד ארבעים וחמשים זוז ad arbaim ve'chamishim zuz forty or fifty זוז
zuz like a lot of
money okay so ten times as much obviously an exaggeration. במה דברים
אמורים בזמן שאין שם פועלים לשכור bamei devarim amurim bizman she'ein sham
po'alim liskor now that's only that you can deceive them or hire
people at exorbitant rates is if you can't find easy replacements. אבל
היו שם פועלים לשכור aval hayu sham po'alim liskor if you can
find easy replacements ואמר צאו שכרו מאלו ve'amar tze'u sechoru me'eilu
and they basically say look we're quitting in the middle of the
day yes it's a דבר אבוד davar avud but go go back
to the place where all the workers are hanging out and go
hire some other workers. In that case אין לו עליהן אלא תרעומת
ein lo aleihen ella taromet you only have a complaint okay it's
a דבר אבוד davar avud but nevertheless I can hire replacements. Okay
so the basic חידוש here was right there was two things not
in our משנה one was an opinion that even when the workers
back out in the middle of the day they're protected from any
from any loss that's the so our משנה was רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa who said no I get to withhold the amount withhold from
them the amount of loss that they caused me. And the other
was after they've shown up if I'm the one who backs out
I have to pay them their full day's wages. Okay so fine
and tomorrow we'll start I want to read this little תוספות that
discusses the questions raised about what about lost opportunity and what about
expense and those types of things so we'll start with that תוספות
and then we'll continue. Okay we'll pick up with that tomorrow.
Okay Rabbi Dosa.